Based on and inspired by the teachings of Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi, this series
Inspiriert von den Lehren Shri Mataji Nirmala Devis,
aims to explore the evolutionary relationship between two interconnected domains
beschäftigt sich diese Serie mit der Evolution zweier Ausdrucksformen
expressing human awareness at the gross and subtle levels.
des menschlichen Bewusstseins auf der grob- und feinstofflichen Ebene.
It endeavors to elucidate this complex interplay between the current scientific understanding
Die Serie beleuchtet das komplexe Zusammenspiel
of human neuroanatomy; the autonomic nervous system in particular,
zwischen dem autonomen Nervensystem
and the so-called subtle system as described in the traditional literature on yoga.
und dem feinstofflichen System der traditionellen Yoga-Lehren.
Ultimately, the series tries to bring its viewers along this exploratory journey
Die Zuschauer werden in diese Entdeckungsreise einbezogen,
to experience these relationships through meditation as taught by Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi.
um diese Beziehung durch eine Meditation mit Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi zu erfahren.
The human brain is a universe within us, and understanding its complex geography
Die Komplexität des inneren Universums unseres Gehirns zu verstehen,
is a grand adventure of our time, said David Van Essen.
ist nach David van Essen ein großes Abenteuer unserer Zeit.
Also, the relationship between the brain and spirituality has been studied
Die Beziehung zwischen Gehirn und Spiritualität wurde
by several different fields,
aus verschiedenen Perspektiven betrachtet,
and we are also on this very fascinating exploration
und auch wir unternehmen diese faszinierende Entdeckungsreise
with our esteemed guest, Dr. Ashish Pradhan,
mit Dr. Ashish Pradhan, unserem geschätzten Gast,
who is a neurologist, a meditation practitioner, and a coach.
Neurologen, Praktizierenden von Sahaja Yoga und Übungsleiter.
So without any delay, I would like to welcome Dr. Ashish on the program.
Ohne Umschweife heiße ich Ashish nun willkommen.
Welcome, doctor.
Willkommen, Doktor.
How are you?
Wie geht es Ihnen?
I'm very well, thanks, Monika.
Mir geht es sehr gut. Danke, Monika.
Glad to see you again.
Ich freue mich, Sie wiederzusehen.
It's really nice always talking to you.
Es ist immer wieder schön, mit Ihnen zu sprechen.
You bring such wealth of information,
Sie bringen viele Informationen mit,
and I am really looking forward to talking to you
und ich freue mich sehr darauf, heute mit Ihnen
about the sixth energy center today.
über das sechste Energiezentrum zu sprechen.
We would like to start with that question
Wir würden gerne etwas über die Beziehung
of the relationship between the sixth energy center and the autonomic nervous system,
des sechsten Energiezentrums zum vegetativen Nervensystem erfahren
and what organs the center controls.
und welche Organe dieses Zentrum steuert.
As we have seen in the first part of this series,
In den ersten Folgen dieser Serie sprachen wir
the first five energy centers,
über die ersten fünf Energiezentren und darüber
the way the energy center potentially looks after the plexuses,
wie ein Energiezentrum potenziell die Plexus
and through the plexuses
des autonomen Nervensystems versorgt und durch sie
of the autonomic nervous system has influence over various organs
Einfluss auf verschiedene Organe
within the body.
des Körpers nimmt.
So today, we are going to talk about again,
Heute sprechen wir über ein weiteres
a very important, critical center.
entscheidendes Zentrum.
So this is the sixth energy center, the so-called Agnya chakra.
Es ist das sechste Energiezentrum, das sogenannte ‘Agnya Chakra’.
A lot has been written about it in multiple spiritual treatises,
In vielen spirituellen Abhandlungen wurde viel darüber geschrieben,
It is also referred to as the third eye in spirituality.
und in der Spiritualität wird es auch als das ‘Dritte Auge’ bezeichnet.
The Agnya chakra, or the sixth energy center,
Wie alle Energiezentren, ist das Agnya Chakra
is, as all of these energy centers go, very, very subtle.
sehr subtil.
It is located at a midpoint, one might say,
Es befindet sich am Schnittpunkt zweier gedachter Linien
if we draw a line from the center of the forehead to the back,
von der Mitte der Stirn nach hinten
and from the top of the ears,
und zwischen den Oberkanten der Ohren
where it crosses, at that intersection deep within our brain.
tief in unserem Gehirn.
The physical manifestation of this energy center,
Physisch könnte es sich
not the energy center itself, but the manifestation of this,
als ‘Chiasma opticum’
could be in the form of the optic chiasma.
manifestieren.
What is optic chiasma?
Was ist das Chiasma opticum?
So, we have our eyes and the retina
Die Netzhaut (Retina) unserer Augen
that is at the back of the eye, that is the back end.
befindet sich auf der Rückseite der Augen.
From the retina, you have nerves, and these nerves have their cell bodies.
Von der Netzhaut gehen aus Nervenzellen gebildete Nerven aus.
The axons from these bodies form the nerves,
Die Fortsätze (Axone) dieser Nervenzellen
which together make up the optic nerve.
bilden zusammen den Sehnerv.
The optic nerve is a collection of these axons, or these long tails.
Der Sehnerv ist eine Ansammlung dieser langen Fortsätze.
And the optic nerves from each, the left and the right eye,
Die Sehnerven des linken und des rechten Auges
they go back and they cross over.
verlaufen nach hinten und überkreuzen sich.
That's called optic chiasma.
Diese Stelle nennt man Chiasma opticum.
And they cross over and then they go and they terminate at the back of the brain,
Sie überkreuzen sich und verlaufen zum hinteren Teil des Gehirns,
in what is called the occipital cortex.
wo sie im okzipitalen Kortex enden.
So the impulses from the eye, the light that goes in
Das Licht fällt durch die Pupillen auf die Netzhaut
through our pupils falls on the retina, creates a chemical reaction,
und erzeugt dort eine chemische Reaktion.
and that impulse travels back and through the various connections that it has,
Dann wandert dieser Impuls über die Nerven in den hinteren Teil des Gehirns,
it interprets vision, or what it is that we are seeing.
der wiederum das interpretiert, was wir sehen.
So the physical manifestation is considered to be the optic chiasma,
Das Chiasma opticum wird als die physische Manifestation angesehen,
but that's not the energy center.
aber nicht als das Energiezentrum selbst.
This energy center controls our eyes,
Es steuert also unsere Augen
our vision in terms of what it sees, what it interprets.
und interpretiert das, was wir sehen.
So that's the first part.
Das ist der erste Teil.
The second organ this energy center relates to is the master,
Das zweite, von diesem Energiezentrum gesteuerte Organ
or the conductor of the orchestra.
ist der Dirigent des Orchesters.
You see, like a big philharmonic orchestra,
Wie bei einem großen Philharmonieorchester gibt es einen Dirigenten,
there is a conductor - and that conductor is the hypothalamus.
und dieser Dirigent ist der Hypothalamus.
The hypothalamus is a very small organ situated in the middle of our brain.
Der Hypothalamus ist ein sehr kleines Organ in der Mitte des Gehirns.
And we'll talk more about it also in the context of the limbic system,
Wir sprechen noch im Kontext des limbischen Systems
which is the seven so-called energy center complex.
und des siebten Energiezentrums darüber.
But the hypothalamus is an organ that sits at the crossroads
Der Hypothalamus bildet die Schnittstelle
between the endocrine system and the nervous system.
zwischen endokrinem und Nervensystem.
So it secretes a number of hormones.
Er produziert viele Hormone,
And these hormones in turn control other endocrine organs,
die wiederum andere endokrine Systeme steuern wie etwa:
such as the pituitary, such as the adrenal cortex,
die Hypophyse, die Nebennierenrinden
such as the male and the female reproductive endocrine systems
und die reproduktiven endokrinen Systeme
that give rise to the ovarian cycle or the spermatogenesis in males,
zur Regulierung der Spermatogenese bei Männern
ovarian cycles in females.
oder der Eierstockzyklen bei Frauen.
So the hypothalamus has four or five key functions.
Der Hypothalamus hat somit vier oder fünf Schlüsselfunktionen.
And the first one is to maintain the internal homeostasis
Er hält die innere Homöostase aufrecht,
by regulating the temperature and the basic biological functions
indem er Körpertemperatur und grundlegende biologische Funktionen
through the autonomic nervous system.
durch das autonome Nervensystem reguliert.
So that includes our blood pressure, that includes our thirst,
Das schließt Blutdruck, Durst sowie
our hunger or our appetite.
unseren Hunger oder Appetit ein.
It controls our urges.
Er kontrolliert unsere Triebe
It regulates our body temperature as well.
und unsere Körpertemperatur.
It has endocrine functions,
Durch seine endokrinen Funktionen
and through the hormones it secretes,
und von ihm produzierte Hormone
it also controls the autonomic nervous system
reguliert er
via these secretions.
das autonome Nervensystem.
So say, for example, the adrenal cortex secretes cortisol,
Die Nebennierenrinde etwa
and that is our stress hormone.
sondert das Stresshormon Kortisol ab.
So flight and fight reactions, for example,
Die Kampf- oder Fluchtreaktion
which is a very well-known response within human physiology,
ist sehr bekannt in der menschlichen Physiologie:
you see something that is a grave danger, you run away from it.
Man erkennt eine große Gefahr und rennt davor weg,
Or if it is something you want to overcome, you fight it.
oder man will sie überwinden und bekämpft sie.
So all of these are controlled through this hormonal system.
Dies wird alles durch dieses Hormonsystem gesteuert.
The hormonal system receives input -
Es erhält einen Input
the hypothalamus gets signals from multiple nervous systems.
durch den Hypothalamus und Signale aus verschiedenen Nervensystemen.
This enables it
Dies ermöglicht es ihm,
to control the functioning of the body.
die Körperfunktionen zu steuern.
And that hypothalamus is believed to be under the control of this sixth energy center.
Da man annimmt, dass der Hypothalamus vom sechsten Energiezentrum kontrolliert wird,
So you can say that the sixth energy center practically is the lord and master
könnte man sagen, dass dieses Energiezentrum praktisch
or mistress of the autonomic nervous system.
der Herr und Meister des vegetativen Nervensystems ist.
So as part of this series, we have now reached a point
Jetzt haben wir also einen Punkt erreicht,
where we talk about the master control of this entire orchestra,
an dem wir über die Hauptsteuerung des ganzen Orchesters sprechen.
and that is the hypothalamus.
Das ist der Hypothalamus –
So that is another very important organ
ein sehr wichtiges Organ,
that this center refers to.
das mit dem sechsten Energiezentrum zusammenhängt.
The third organ that we would want to consider in this context
Das dritte Organ, das wir betrachten wollen,
is the pineal gland.
ist die Zirbeldrüse.
The pineal gland is a very, very small body that also sits very close to the hypothalamus.
Die sehr kleine Zirbeldrüse sitzt ebenfalls nahe beim Hypothalamus.
And this pineal body secretes a hormone you're all familiar with,
Sie sondert ein Hormon ab, das Sie alle kennen.
it's called melatonin.
Es heißt Melatonin.
And melatonin controls our sleep cycle.
Melatonin steuert unseren Schlafzyklus.
It's extremely important.
Es ist extrem wichtig.
Anyone who's crossed time zones knows jet lag -
Alle, die einmal Zeitzonen durchquert haben, kennen den Jetlag.
it's caused by the circadian rhythm,
Er entsteht durch den zirkadianen Rhythmus.
the 24-hour sleep cycle controlled by melatonin.
Auch als 24-Stunden-Zyklus bezeichnet, wird er durch Melatonin gesteuert
As the sun goes down, as the light goes down,
Geht die Sonne unter oder nimmt das Licht ab,
melatonin secretion starts going up.
steigt die Melatonin-Ausschüttung.
And that is controlled by the pineal gland.
Sie wird von der Zirbeldrüse gesteuert.
So within that framework, if we go back to the Sahaj subtle system,
Wenden wir uns wieder dem feinstofflichen System von Sahaja Yoga zu,
you have the left side, which is the so-called passive side,
gibt es eine linke passive Seite
you have the right side, the so-called active side
sowie eine rechte aktive Seite
that we have in the subtle system within our body,
im feinstofflichen System unseres Körpers.
and then of course, the evolutionary side, which is the central channel.
Dann gibt es noch den evolutionären Teil des Zentralkanals.
So you can see how there is a beautiful correlation between the function
Man erkennt also einen wunderbaren Zusammenhang
of the hypothalamus by regulating the body's requirements.
mit der Funktion des Hypothalamus, der die Bedürfnisse des Körpers reguliert:
In the morning, we feel hungry, at night, not so much after we have had the day,
Morgens haben wir Hunger und nachts, nach dem Tagwerk, nicht mehr so sehr.
the whole body temperature actually starts falling down towards the evening,
Die Körpertemperatur beginnt, gegen Abend zu sinken
and it reaches its lowest temperature at night,
und erreicht nachts ihren niedrigsten Wert.
which is why we sleep better in the cooler environments.
Darum schlafen wir in kühleren Umgebungen besser
If it's very hot, we can't sleep very well.
und bei Hitze nicht gut.
And it is also believed that when the body temperature starts going down,
Man nimmt auch an, dass eine sinkende Körpertemperatur
it starts inducing the state that we call sleep,
den Schlaf einleitet
that we just lie down and go to sleep.
und wir uns einfach hinlegen und einschlafen.
Through this energy center, we can say that
Wir können sagen, dass dieses Energiezentrum
by monitoring our internal body through the autonomic nervous system,
unseren Körper über das autonome Nervensystem überwacht
by managing our sleep cycle,
und unseren Schlafzyklus steuert.
it manages our both: passive behaviors such as sleep
Dadurch kontrolliert es unser passives Verhalten wie den Schlaf
but also the active side,
und die tagsüber die aktive Seite,
which happens during the daytime, when melatonin levels are very low.
wenn der Melatoninspiegel sehr niedrig ist.
So it is this magnificently managed control,
Diese großartige Steuerung wird erreicht
extremely finely done by regulation of the nervous system
über die Feinabstimmung des Nervensystems, das wiederum
to these two or three organs that relate
diese zwei oder drei Organe kontrolliert,
to the sixth energy center.
die dem sechsten Energiezentrum zugeordnet werden.
As laymen we seldom get a chance to understand
Als Laien haben wir selten Gelegenheit
or admire these complex communications,
diese komplexen Kommunikationen
rhythms and patterns that have been designed into us.
und diese in uns angelegten Rhythmen und Muster zu würdigen.
This is really very, very wonderful information, Dr. Ashish.
Das sind wunderbare Informationen, Dr. Pradhan.
We would like to know the evolutionary significance
Gerne würden wir etwas über die evolutionäre Bedeutung
and where the center is most likely located?
und die Lokalisierung dieses Zentrums erfahren?
So this center - hypothalamus - as you can imagine,
Die körperliche Regulierung eines Organismus
the regulation of the body of an organism was a requirement
durch den Hypothalamus
from an evolutionary point of view,
war eine evolutionäre Anforderung.
it's putting maybe the cart before the horse
Doch das zäumt das Pferd von hinten auf
or effect before the cause.
und setzt die Wirkung vor die Ursache.
But even as we start looking at again, the aquatic life forms,
Frühe aquatische Lebensformen,
and then amphibians and early terrestrial, so on and so forth,
Amphibien und frühe Landlebewesen,
as the bodies became more complex, multicellular with more
brauchten mit zunehmender Komplexität, Mehrzelligkeit
and more defined organ systems, cardiovascular system,
und differenzierteren Herz-Kreislauf-,
respiratory system, digestive system,
Atmungs- und Verdauungssystemen
they needed a master control over that organism so as to survive.
eine zentrale Steuerung, um zu überleben.
If any of these systems are not well controlled, it can go out of whack,
Wird eines dieser Systeme nicht gut kontrolliert, kann es aus dem Ruder laufen,
and then that starts creating its own issues.
und eigene Probleme schaffen.
So which is why the hypothalamus is believed
Daher wird angenommen, dass hypothalamische Neuronen,
that hypothalamic nuclei, like any organ in the brain,
wie jedes Organ im Gehirn,
is like anything else, it's just a group of cells.
eine Zellgruppe sind wie alle anderen auch.
So anything in the brain is composed of cells that are called neurons.
Alles im Gehirn besteht aus den sogenannten Neuronen.
The hypothalamic neurons, maybe not the organ,
Hypothalamische Neuronen
but the neurons have been found in very primitive life forms as well.
wurden bereits in sehr primitiven Lebensformen gefunden.
So that is the evolutionary relevance of this particular energy center, if you will,
Darin liegt die evolutionäre Relevanz dieses Energiezentrums
as manifest through the existence of the anatomical organ,
und seiner Manifestation als anatomisches Organ
which is manifest in vertebrates,
bei Wirbeltieren und insbesondere
and particularly, of course, in the Homo sapiens as hypothalamus.
beim Homo sapiens als Hypothalamus.
So its evolutionary significance is profound,
Seine evolutionäre Bedeutung ist also grundlegend.
without the hypothalamus or a hypothalamic like body,
Durch den Hypothalamus oder ein ihm ähnliches Organ,
controlling the entirety of our vegetative functions,
das alle autonomen Funktionen steuert,
which is why we don't have to think about how many times our heart has to beat,
müssen wir nicht darüber nachdenken,
we don't have to think
wie oft unser Herz schlagen muss
what should be the force of the digestive propulsive forces?
oder wie stark die treibenden Kräfte der Verdauung sein sollten.
How many times should we breathe?
Wie oft sollten wir atmen?
What is the extent of breathing?
Wie tief sollten wir atmen?
All of these functions, that is circulatory system,
Für alle Funktionen wie das Kreislauf-,
respiratory system or digestive system,
das Atmungs- oder Verdauungssystem
and the thousands and thousands of processes in the body that are controlled,
und die Abertausend Prozesse im Körper
that needed that sort of system - you can think of it as,
war ein Steuerungssystem nötig.
as almost like a fly-by-wire technology that exists now in modern aircraft,
Dies funktioniert ähnlich einem digitalen Flugsteuerungssystem:
but the pilot doesn't really have to think,
Der Pilot muss nicht wirklich nachdenken,
just switches on as a master computer that takes over
sondern steuert nur über einen Hauptcomputer,
and on a second to second, not even a minute to minute,
der in jeder Sekunde
just as the aircraft maintains its altitude, its speed, its direction,
Höhe, Geschwindigkeit und Richtung reguliert.
that's exactly how the hypothalamus functions.
Genauso funktioniert der Hypothalamus.
And that is its evolutionary significance.
Das ist seine evolutionäre Bedeutung.
It has evolved to allow us to survive
Er hat sich entwickelt, um uns das Überleben zu ermöglichen,
without having to put in a lot of cognitive effort,
ohne dass wir großen kognitiven
conscious effort into our survival.
oder bewussten Aufwand dafür betreiben müssen.
So that's basically its evolutionary importance.
Das ist seine evolutionäre Bedeutung.
It is located
Das sechste Energiezentrum befindet sich wahrscheinlich
just maybe below the optic chiasma that we spoke about.
direkt unter dem Chiasma opticum,
And it is again, very difficult to maybe just pinpoint
obwohl es schwierig ist, es genau zu lokalisieren.
because it exists in the form of energy.
Denn es existiert als Energie.
We discussed that in one of the first episodes.
Wir sprachen in einer der ersten Episoden darüber,
So these don't exist in the state of matter,
das diese Energiezentren nicht als Materie existieren.
but it's most likely situated, as we said,
Doch es liegt höchstwahrscheinlich
you draw a straight line from the middle of her forehead,
am Schnittpunkt einer Linie von der Mitte der Stirn direkt nach hinten
right at the back, and then from across from the top of her ears.
und einer von einer Oberkante der Ohren zur anderen.
And where these two lines will intersect somewhere in the middle,
Wo sich diese beiden Linien direkt unter dem Chiasma opticum
just below the optic chiasma in that area
und in der Nähe des Hypothalamus schneiden,
is where near the hypothalamus is probably where this energy center is located.
liegt der wahrscheinliche Sitz dieses Energiezentrums.
I really like the analogies that you use to explain complex concepts,
Mir gefallen Ihre Analogien zur Erklärung komplexer Zusammenhänge.
because if we do not have a lot of science background,
Denn ohne wissenschaftlichen Hintergrund wird es für uns so viel einfacher,
it just gets so much easier for us to just understand that whole concept.
das ganze Konzept zu verstehen.
That's very, very beautifully explained, doctor.
Das ist eine schöne Erklärung, Doktor.
When we come to the functioning of the center,
Wie hängt die Funktionsweise des sechsten Zentrums
how does it relate to the maintenance of balance
mit der Aufrechterhaltung des Gleichgewichts
within a human being?
im Menschen zusammen?
And is there, is this related to a direct control of actions, emotions,
Gibt es einen Zusammenhang mit der Regulierung von Handlungen und Emotionen,
the active passive aspects of human behavior?
also den aktiven und passiven Aspekten des menschlichen Verhaltens?
Absolutely.
Absolut.
So as we said, the neuroendocrine system is closely linked to —
Das neuroendokrine System ist eng verbunden mit ...
there's so much literature on stress and stress management
Es gibt umfangreiche Literatur über Stress, seine Bewältigung
and what causes stress and whether stress is even
und Ursachen und ob Stress – physiologisch gesehen –
a physiologically good thing to have because it is something called eustress,
vielleicht auch etwas Gutes ist; denn es gibt so etwas
distress, so on and so forth.
wie Eustress und Distress usw.
But when we look at the normal physiologic functioning of a human being,
Doch die normale Physiologie eines Menschen
it comprises a minute to minute or even a second to second awareness
umfasst eine von Sekunde zu Sekunde reichende Wahrnehmung
of our own selves as well as that of our surroundings.
unserer selbst und unserer Umgebung.
And it brings into focus our attention, our memories,
Sie rückt unsere Aufmerksamkeit und Erinnerungen in den Fokus,
and we'll talk about this, of course, in the next episode as well.
worüber wir auch in der nächsten Folge sprechen.
Our memories, attention, our awareness,
... unsere Erinnerungen, unsere Aufmerksamkeit, unser Bewusstsein,
our place within the universe around us,
unser Platz im Universum,
whether it is our societies, whether it is our families,
unsere Gesellschaft, unsere Familie
whether it is our workplaces.
oder unser Arbeitsplatz ...
And in this minute to minute, literally, existential sort of environment,
In dieser sich fortlaufend ändernden existenziellen Umgebung
we react, we respond.
reagieren und antworten wir.
And we respond in a way that is a very complex integral,
Wir antworten als Individuum
if you will, of who we are as individuals.
auf eine sehr komplexe und integrierende Weise.
And who we are as individuals is again a function of our collective past,
Dabei wird unsere Individualität von unserer kollektiven
our individual past, our cultures, our ethnic identities,
und individuellen Vergangenheit, unserer Kultur und Ethnie,
our languages, our geographies, where we come from,
unserer Sprache und Geografie sowie
the way we were raised, not everybody's raised the same.
unserer Erziehung bestimmt.
So whoever we are, this huge amalgam of our memories,
Diese riesige Mischung aus Erinnerungen
of our conditionings, all are governed by what constitutes the brain.
und Konditionierungen wird von unserem Gehirn gesteuert.
And within the brain, it is this energy center that plays a particular role,
Im Gehirn spielt das sechste Energiezentrum eine besondere Rolle,
because it is also related to the notion of ego and superego.
weil es auch mit den Begriffen von Ego und Superego zusammenhängt.
And we have these two institutions, there are other videos
Diese beiden Institutionen werden in anderen
that Sahaja Yoga gives us, that speak to it,
Sahaja-Yoga-Videos besprochen.
but it gives you that sense of I-ness versus the others.
Doch Ego und Superego vermitteln unser Ich-Gefühl,
And that is where this energy center comes into play.
und hier kommt dieses Energiezentrum ins Spiel.
So in individuals who are well balanced,
Sehr ausgeglichene Menschen reagieren
'balanced' is more of a metaphorical term
metaphorisch oder spirituell gesehen
or of a spiritual term, but individuals who do not react
nicht unnötig
unnecessarily or excessively,
oder übermäßig.
if you see a cat and you start running in the opposite direction, that's a problem.
Sieht man eine Katze und läuft davon, ist das ein Problem.
If you see a tiger and you start running in the opposite direction, not a problem.
Sieht man einen Tiger und läuft davon, ist das kein Problem.
Why?
Warum?
Because although they both belong to the cat family,
Obwohl beide zur Katzenfamilie gehören,
those are two very different situations.
sind es zwei sehr unterschiedliche Situationen.
So that is where this center comes into play.
An diesem Punkt kommt dieses Zentrum ins Spiel:
And if there are individuals who react in a very different way,
Es gibt Menschen, die in solchen
in these kinds of situations, those are very generic situations,
sehr allgemeinen und offensichtlichen Situationen
very obvious ones.
ganz anders reagieren.
But that is what defines a healthy state of this energy center versus not.
Doch diese Reaktionen definieren einen gesunden Zustand dieses Zentrums oder eben nicht.
And therefore, it is very important to keep this energy center
Daher ist es wichtig, auch dieses Energiezentrum
in a very healthy state or might say in a balanced state
in einem guten Zustand zu halten,
by developing through the Sahaj meditation process,
indem man durch Sahaja Yoga
what we call a balanced, forgiving and a charitably disposed personality.
eine ausgeglichene, nachsichtige und wohlwollende Persönlichkeit entwickelt.
Because that way, as you can now see the function of the hypothalamus,
Auf diese Weise muss der Hypothalamus
it does not have to secrete these hormones that will raise your blood pressure,
keine Hormone produzieren, die den Blutdruck
that will raise your heart rate, that will allow you to react more aggressively
oder die Herzfrequenz erhöhen oder die uns auf eine Umgebung
to an environment which you perceive to be aggressive,
aggressiv reagieren lassen, die wir als aggressiv wahrnehmen.
which may not be aggressive, which may not be threatening to you.
Vielleicht ist sie gar nicht aggressiv oder bedrohlich für uns.
So life then becomes more a matter of perception rather than reality.
Das Leben wird so mehr zu einer Frage der Wahrnehmung als der Realität.
And the calibration of one's response to that environment
Die Kalibrierung der eigenen Reaktion auf unsere Umgebung
is what defines an individual from being relatively
definiert ein Individuum konventionell als reaktiv und unreif
what we call in conventional terms as reactive, immature,
oder als jemanden,
to somebody who is, we say, more mature, sagacious.
der reifer und weiser ist.
So think of a Lincoln or a Gandhi like personality
Denken wir an Lincoln oder Gandhi im Vergleich zu Persönlichkeiten
relative to somebody who is much more reactive or gets easily ruffled,
die viel reaktiver sind oder sich leicht aus der Ruhe bringen lassen.
we say, we just know some people who are just calm, more composed,
Wir kennen Menschen, die ruhiger und gelassener sind
they don't react that negatively or excessively.
und nicht so negativ oder übermäßig reagieren.
And that is where it kind of comes in, the importance of this center
Bei der Wahrung des richtigen Handlungsgleichgewichts
to maintain that balance within us, right action and right behavior.
kommt dieses Zentrums ins Spiel.
It does not mean we remain constantly passive.
Das bedeutet nicht, ständig passiv
we remain constantly active.
oder aktiv zu sein.
Where is that fine balance?
Wo befindet sich dieses feine Gleichgewicht?
How do you calibrate back to that aircraft?
Wie kalibriert man dieses Flugzeug?
How do you maintain your speed, your altitude and your course
Wie hält man seine Geschwindigkeit, seine Höhe und seinen Kurs
from a, shall we say, an emotional perspective
aus emotionaler oder spiritueller Perspektive?
or from a spiritual perspective is what this center is really about.
Darum geht es bei diesem Zentrum,
And that's why it plays such a vital role in human spirituality.
und deshalb spielt es eine so wichtige spirituelle Rolle.
Thank you, Dr. Ashish, for bringing up that very wonderful point,
Danke, Dr. Pradhan, dass Sie diesen Punkt ansprechen.
a very relevant point about the level of reactions that we all may have.
Er ist sehr wichtig im Hinblick auf unsere Reaktionen.
And it is for each of us to, just look inside us, look around us
Es liegt an uns, introspektiv zu erkennen,
to see where we find just giving reactions more than needed.
wo wir mehr als nötig reagieren
Like you explained with the example of the cat and the tiger responses
und das Beispiel mit der Katze und dem Tiger zeigt uns
to a similar situation or a different situation,
wie unsere Reaktionen in solchen Situationen
how they need to be.
sein sollten.
But this is something that we are seeing a lot around us on social media
So etwas sehen wir häufig in den sozialen Medien
and different platforms.
und auf verschiedenen Plattformen.
So, anything that you want to add to that
Möchten Sie dem noch etwas hinzufügen,
just so that we can be more aware of our surroundings,
damit wir uns unserer Umgebung und Umwelt
our environments where we are?
bewusster werden?
Fabulous. That's such a great point, Monika,
Das ist ein guter Hinweis, Monika.
if we think of our evolution,
Aus evolutionärer Sicht müssen wir nicht
but we don't have to go back to the aquatic stage.
bis zu den aquatischen Stadien zurückgehen.
Just about 100 years ago, just about 50 years ago,
Vor etwa 100 oder 50 Jahren
there was no social media,
gab es keine sozialen Medien.
television and media did not play such a big role in our lives.
Fernsehen und Medien spielten keine so große Rolle in unserem Leben.
People had a much more quote-unquote pastoral lifestyle,
Die Menschen vorindustrieller Gesellschaften
certainly pre-industrial societies.
hatten einen viel ländlicheren Lebensstil.
But even in post-industrial societies, it was not that much of a deal.
Doch selbst in postindustriellen Gesellschaften
This influence of media and the environment around us,
war der Einfluss von Medien und Umwelt keine so große Sache.
there were communities, there were neighbors,
Es gab Gemeinschaften und Nachbarn,
but with the advent of social media, particularly, life has become very reactive.
aber mit den sozialen Medien ist das Leben sehr reaktiv geworden.
You are part of some kind of a social media platform,
Mit Freunden, Kollegen oder Nachbarn
whichever it is, with your friends, with your office colleagues or neighbours,
ist man Teil einer Social-Media-Plattform.
as the case may be, you read a post about a topic,
Man liest Beiträge über politische
whether it is political, whether it is social, whether it is cultural,
soziale oder kulturelle Themen,
and the brain processes it.
und das Gehirn verarbeitet es.
Within our brain is a very important group
In unserem Gehirn gibt es wichtige Neurotransmitter
of neurotransmitters - one of them is dopamine.
und einer davon ist Dopamin.
Dopamine is a pleasure giving molecule.
Dopamin ist ein Molekül, das Vergnügen bereitet.
Whenever we do or feel something pleasurable,
Immer wenn wir etwas Angenehmes tun oder fühlen,
there is a part of the brain called a substantia nigra that secretes dopamine.
schüttet ein Hirnbereich namens Substantia nigra Dopamin aus.
Dopamine gives us that high, that rush.
Dopamin beschert uns dieses Hochgefühl, diesen Rausch;
And where social media comes in, social media algorithms.
und da kommen die Algorithmen der sozialen Medien ins Spiel.
I'm not a tech expert, but I saw a couple of documentaries,
Zwar bin ich kein Technikexperte, doch einige Dokumentationen
and they explained beautifully that there is a full blown understanding
zeigten sehr anschaulich das ausgereifte wissenschaftliche Verständnis
of the human nervous system, and particularly of how the dopamine
des Nervensystems und insbesondere wie das Dopamin-System
system works to produce that rush.
diesen Rausch erzeugt.
So we are constantly through algorithms that are designed to generate that rush within us.
Ständig werden wir durch ‘berauschende’ Algorithmen beeinflusst
So we are constantly hooked onto it.
und sind daran gefesselt.
We are given content or fed content that is based on these algorithms
Inhalte werden an uns verfüttert, die auf diesen Algorithmen basieren
that grab our attention and hold it.
und die unsere Aufmerksamkeit fesseln und fixieren.
And that is where this center is also where it's damaged the most,
Dadurch wird dieses Zentrum sehr geschädigt,
because it keeps us on this endless loop.
da sie uns in dieser Endlosschleife halten.
We are essentially like animals that are on treadmills,
Wir sind wie Tiere auf einem Laufband,
that you're constantly fed that morphine of information, if you will,
die man ständig mit dem Informationsmorphin füttert.
and that triggers dopamine within us.
Das löst die Produktion von Dopamin in uns aus
And that gives us that sense of high and that high keeps us hooked onto social media.
und beschert uns dieses Hochgefühl, das uns an die sozialen Medien fesselt.
So the Agnya Chakra or the sixth energy center probably in the entirety of human civilization,
Wahrscheinlich war das Agnya Chakra in der dokumentierten
recorded and unrecorded history, and this is not a hyperbole,
und nicht dokumentierten Geschichte
I genuinely feel it has never probably been more stressed due to social media.
noch nie so sehr durch soziale Medien gestresst.
But what is the solution?
Worin liegt die Lösung?
It's easy to identify a problem, but then what is the solution?
Ein Problem ist einfach zu erkennen, aber worin liegt die Lösung?
The solution is that through meditation,
Die Lösung besteht darin, dass wir durch Meditation anfangen,
we can begin to stay away from that rush.
uns von diesem Rausch fernzuhalten.
We don't need that rush.
Wir brauchen diesen Rausch nicht.
You don't need to constantly feel your presence on social media
Man muss nicht ständig in den sozialen Medien präsent sein,
or see what is the latest post out there?
den neuesten Beitrag kennen oder prüfen,
Or if you posted something, has somebody read it or not?
ob jemand den eigenen Post gelesen hat.
How many likes have you received?
Wie viele Likes hat man
Or have you not received it?
oder hat man nicht bekommen?
So if you have not received anything, no responses,
Hat man keine Antworten erhalten,
you kind of go down and then that dopamine rush goes down,
gerät man in ein Tief, der Dopaminrausch lässt nach,
you'll start feeling depressed.
und man fühlt sich deprimiert.
And we see this particularly in teenagers,
Das sehen wir besonders bei Teenagern.
which is why the US Congress is acting very wisely.
Daher handelt der US-Kongress sehr weise,
So to try to see if these social media platforms
wenn er versucht, Social-Media-Plattformen
can actually be modulated
zu modulieren, um psychische Probleme
to avoid creating mental health issues
bei anfälligen Altersgruppen wie Teenagern
for susceptible age groups such as teenagers,
zu vermeiden, deren Nutzungsstrukturen
whose use can lead to extreme outcomes.
zu extremen Ergebnissen führen können.
So yes, that's a phenomenal point that you raised.
Das ist ein phänomenaler Punkt.
And this energy center in particular plays a very critical role
Das sechste Energiezentrum spielt dabei eine entscheidende Rolle,
in either being susceptible and being influenced by social media.
da es empfänglich ist und von sozialen Medien beeinflusst werden kann.
But then through meditative practice, such as the Sahaj meditation,
Durch die meditative Praxis des Sahaja Yoga
you can actually maintain a healthy boundary.
kann man tatsächlich eine gesunde Grenze aufrechterhalten.
So nobody's saying here, you should not interact with social media,
Niemand behauptet, man solle keine sozialen Medien nutzen.
not use social media, social media is a way of life now.
Sie sind heute ein Teil des Lebens
We all have to live with it.
und wir alle müssen damit leben.
The question is how and to what extent?
Die Frage ist: "Wie und in welchem Ausmaß?"
And I think with what you have shared, it seems like,
Mit dem, was Sie mit uns geteilt haben, scheint es,
with this meditation, not only an individual is going to benefit,
dass von dieser Meditation nicht nur jeder Einzelne
in the ability to self-regulate themselves,
von der Fähigkeit profitiert, sich selbst zu regulieren.
it'll also impact the society at large.
Es wird auch die Gesellschaft als Ganzes beeinflussen.
Think about it like, if each of us just gets a little bit better
Wenn wir alle unsere Reaktionsweisen
in terms of how we react,
nur etwas verbessern,
it's really going to impact the health of the society as well.
wird das auch die gesellschaftliche Gesundheit beeinflussen.
Thank you, Dr. Ashish.
Danke, Dr. Pradhan.
Thank you so much for this very wonderful information.
Vielen Dank für diese wertvollen Informationen.
And we look forward to speaking to you again soon next time.
Wir freuen uns, bald wieder mit Ihnen zu sprechen.
Thank you Monika, thanks for having me.
Danke, Monika. Danke für die Einladung.
Thank you.
Vielen Dank.
We would encourage our audiences to follow
Jetzt laden wir unser Publikum wieder zu der
the guided meditation video by the founder of this meditation,
von Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi geleiteten Meditation zur Selbst-Verwirklichung ein.
Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi.
Sie gründete Sahaja Yoga.
And do join us next time for yet another exciting conversation
Begleiten Sie uns auch nächstes Mal
with Dr. Ashish Pradhan.
bei einem weiteren spannenden Gespräch mit Dr. Ashish Pradhan.
Thank you.
Vielen Dank.
Shri Mataji: Today we are going to understand the center of Agnya,
Shri Mataji: Heute lernen wir, das Agnya-Zentrum zu verstehen.
Agnya chakra which is placed on the crossing of the optic chiasma.
Es befindet sich an der Kreuzung des Chiasma opticum.
The nerves that supply the eyes go backwards in the opposite direction,
Die die Augen versorgenden Nerven verlaufen nach hinten,
and wherever they cross, this subtle center is situated.
und das feinstoffliche Zentrum befindet sich dort, wo sie sich kreuzen.
It has a continuous connection with the other center
Es ist durch die Medulla oblongata
through the medulla oblongata.
mit anderen Zentren verbunden.
This center has got two petals and this subtle center on one side
Das Agnya Chakra hat zwei Blütenblätter und wirkt auf der einen Seite durch die Augen
acts through the eyes and at the back of the head where you have some protrusion.
und auf der Rückseite des Kopfes, wo es eine kleine Vorwölbung gibt.
This is the physical side of the center.
Die physische Seite des Zentrums
The people who talk of the third eye, this is the third eye.
wird auch als das Dritte Auge bezeichnet.
Keep your eyes closed.
Haltet eure Augen geschlossen.
First of all, please put your right hand on your heart.
Legt bitte die rechte Hand auf euer Herz.
All the time the left hand is towards Me.
Die linke Hand ist während der ganzen Zeit zu mir gerichtet.
Now, here you have to say in your heart, with all sincerity, Mother, am I the Spirit?
Fragt in eurem Herzen mit aller Aufrichtigkeit: "Mutter, bin ich der Geist?"
Ask the question three times in your heart.
Stellt diese Frage dreimal in eurem Herzen.
This is a very fundamental question.
Das ist eine sehr grundlegende Frage.
Now bring the right hand on to the left hand side of your stomach,
Bringt nun die rechte Hand auf die linke Seite des Bauches,
in the upper part.
im oberen Teil ...
Here press it.
... und drückt hier auf den Bauch.
Now this is the center of your mastery, your guidance, your guru Tattva, as they say.
Dies ist das Zentrum eurer Meisterschaft, eurer Führung und eures ‘Guru-Tattvas’.
So ask a question, Mother, am I my own master?
Fragt also: "Mutter, bin ich mein eigener Meister?
This is the question to be asked three times.
Stellt diese Frage dreimal.
Mother, am I my own master?
"Mutter, bin ich mein eigener Meister?
Now bring your right hand down below in the lower part of the abdomen.
Legt nun eure rechte Hand nach unten auf den unteren Teil des Bauches.
Now this is the center from which all the Divine work is done,
Dies ist das Zentrum, durch das alle göttliche Arbeit,
all the pure work is done.
alle reine Arbeit getan wird.
So to ask six times, because this center has got six petals,
Hier bittet ihr sechsmal  – denn dieses Zentrum hat sechs Blütenblätter:
Mother, please give me pure knowledge.
"Mutter, bitte schenke mir reines Wissen.
Six times you just ask.
Bittet sechsmal darum.
As a result of this asking the Kundalini starts getting awakened.
Als Antwort auf diese Fragen, beginnt die Kundalini zu erwachen.
Now to help the Kundalini to rise you have to cooperate with Her.
Um der Kundalini beim Aufsteigen zu helfen, müsst ihr mit ihr kooperieren.
So please put your right hand on the left hand side
Legt also bitte die rechte Hand auf der linken Seite,
in the upper part of your abdomen and press it on the stomach.
zurück auf den oberen Teil des Bauches, und drückt dort wieder etwas auf diese Stelle.
Now here you have to say with full confidence,
Hier müsst ihr nun voller Vertrauen
to help the Kundalini to rise, Mother, I am my own master.
der Kundalini beim Aufsteigen helfen und sagen: "Mutter, ich bin mein eigener Meister."
This you have to say ten times.
Sagt es zehnmal.
These are the ten commandments which you have to say,
Das sind die zehn Gebote, die ihr sagen müsst:
that Mother, I am my own master.
"Mutter, ich bin mein eigener Meister",
Now, ten times with full confidence.
zehnmal und voller Vertrauen.
Now please raise your right hand to your heart.
Hebt nun eure rechte Hand zum Herzen,
Now here you have to say, again with full confidence,
und sagt wieder vertrauensvoll:
Mother, I am the Spirit.
"Mutter, ich bin der Geist.
This is the truth, you are the Spirit.
Das ist die Wahrheit. Ihr seid der Geist.
But you have to say with full confidence, Mother, I am the Spirit.
Doch sagt es voller Vertrauen: "Mutter, ich bin der Geist."
This you have to say twelve times.
Sagt es zwölfmal.
Now one has to know that God Almighty is the ocean of love.
Nun muss man wissen, dass der Allmächtige Gott der Ozean der Liebe ist.
But above all He is the ocean of forgiveness.
Doch vor allem ist Er der Ozean der Vergebung.
So He forgives.
Also vergibt Er.
Whatever wrong you do He forgives.
Was auch immer ihr Falsches tut – Er vergibt.
So don't feel guilty and put your right hand across
Fühlt euch also nicht schuldig und legt eure rechte Hand
on the left hand side in the corner which is made by your neck and your shoulder.
quer über den Halsansatz der linken Schulter.
Now here you have to say again with full confidence,
Hier sagt ihr wieder voller Vertrauen und sechzehnmal:
sixteen times, Mother, I am not guilty.
"Mutter, ich bin nicht schuldig.
Please say it, Mother, I am not guilty.
Bitte sagt es: "Mutter, ich bin nicht schuldig",
Sixteen times.
sechzehnmal,
I am not guilty at all.
"Ich bin überhaupt nicht schuldig.
Please say it.
Bitte sagt es.
Now raise your hand across on your forehead and it's a very important center.
Legt nun eure Hand quer über die Stirn. Dies ist ein sehr wichtiges Zentrum.
Here you have to say from your heart, Mother, I forgive everyone.
Hier müsst ihr von Herzen sagen: "Mutter, ich vergebe jedem."
Please say it from your heart.
Bitte sagt es von Herzen.
How many times is not the point.
Es ist nicht so wichtig, wie oft.
Mother, I forgive everyone.
"Mutter, ich vergebe jedem.
Now some would say that it's very difficult to forgive.
Manche sagen vielleicht, es sei sehr schwierig zu vergeben.
But it's a myth that we do not forgive or we forgive.
Doch das ist ein Mythos, denn ob wir vergeben oder nicht –
We do not do anything in both the cases.
wir tun in beiden Fällen nichts.
But if we don't forgive then we play into wrong hands.
Wenn wir jedoch nicht vergeben, spielen wir in falsche Hände.
So please say from your heart, Mother, I forgive everyone.
Also sagt bitte von Herzen: "Mutter, ich vergebe jedem."
Now please take your hand on the back agnya, the same center, on the back side of your head
Legt eure Hand jetzt bitte auf das hintere ‘Agnya‘, dasselbe Zentrum auf der Rückseite des Kopfes.
and allow your head to rest on it and push it back a little bit.
Lasst den Kopf auf der Hand ruhen und legt ihn ein wenig zurück.
Now here you have to say for your satisfaction,
Hier sagt nun – zu eurer eigenen Zufriedenheit
because you always feel guilty, that, O Divine, if I have done anything wrong,
und weil ihr Euch oft schuldig fühlt –: "Oh Göttliches, wenn ich etwas falsch gemacht habe,
please forgive me.
bitte vergib mir.
Please forgive me, from your heart.
"Bitte vergib mir" – sagt es von Herzen.
Stretch your hand fully and put your center of your palm
Streckt dann eure Hand vollständig aus und legt die Mitte der Handfläche
on top of the fontanel bone area, which was a very soft bone in your childhood.
oben auf den Bereich der Fontanelle, der in eurer Kindheit noch ein weicher Knochen war.
Press it hard.
Drückt ihn fest.
Press hard your scalp.
Drückt fest auf eure Kopfhaut.
Now you have to move it seven times saying one thing, which you have to ask for,
Bewegt sie nun siebenmal im Uhrzeigersinn und bittet:
Mother, please give us My Self-realization, because I cannot force on you.
"Mutter, bitte gib mir meine Selbst-Verwirklichung!" Ich kann sie euch nicht aufzwingen –
So you have to ask for it.
deshalb müsst ihr darum bitten.
Seven times press it hard and move it seven times very hard.
Drückt die Kopfhaut fest, bewegt sie siebenmal fest im Uhrzeigersinn
Slowly saying that.
und sagt dabei langsam diese Worte.